CONCERNED CITIZENS AGAINST CROSSGATES RECORDS (APAP057) 1979-1984
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates Records1979-1984
nam_apap057
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates
5.05
M. E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, University at Albany, SUNY
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates (CCAC) was organized as an informal group opposed to the construction of the Pyramid Crossgates mall in the summer of 1979.
Access
Access to this record group is unrestricted.
Acquisition Information
All items in this manuscript group were donated to the University Libraries, M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives, by Lindsay Childs.
Administrative History
Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates (CCAC) was organized as an informal group opposed to the construction of the Pyramid Crossgates mall in the summer of 1979. The group developed into a coalition of concerned residents that at one time had over three thousand members from the Town of Guilderland and neighboring communitites. Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates sought to preserve the rural and residential character of their town.
The administration of CCAC consisted of President Rhonda Childs, Treasurer Mary circa Phillips, and a Board of Directors which included the following members: Gregory R. Bell, Margaret McKinley, Donald J. Reeb, Drew Hartyell, and Anita Kershaw. Rhonda Childs and Mary circa Phillips continued as President and Treasurer until CCAC disbanded in 1984 when Crossgates was under construction.
CCAC was involved in hearings and suits against the Town of Guilderland Zoning, Planning, and Conservation Advisory Boards from 1979 to 1983. They initiated a lawsuit on September 18, 1981 against Robert F. Flacke, commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation, the Town of Guilderland Zoning Appeals Board, the Albany County Planning Board, and David Axelrod, M.D., Commissioner of the New York State Department of Health, to overturn the decision made by the Water Merger Vote of August 27, 1980. CCAC was concerned that the construction of Crossgates would lead to a violation of Department of Health regulations protecting the watershed of McKownville.
CCAC was also involved as an intervenor in the 1981 Pyramid application for a special use permit for traffic and parking relief in the Town of Guilderland. From 1979 to 1982, CCAC was involved in a series of suits against Robert F. Flacke, individually and as Commissioner of the New York State Department of Environmental Conservation. Two of the attorneys that represented CCAC during the lawsuits are Joel H. Sachs, of Plunkett and Jaffe, P.C., and George A. Rowland.
[1] Legal Papers. Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing Water Merger Vote, 1979, 1981-1982.
[2] Legal Papers. CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Volume 1, 1982.
Scope and Content Information
The records of Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates include subject files, legal papers, exhibits for hearings before the Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC), and News Clippings. Due to the informal nature of CCAC, the collection does not contain meeting minutes or correspondence of leaders in the organization, that would indicate the development of strategy.
CCAC's campaign against Crossgates Mall is documented by fliers, ads, election material, speeches, and legal documents supporting the suits that CCAC filed against the Town of Guilderland, Department of Environmental Conservation, and Robert F. Flacke. Other documents include permits, briefs, decisions, attorneys' correspondence, hearing submissions, and related material.
Several collections in the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections and Archives provide further information about the construction of Crossgates Mall including the Crossgates Regional Shopping Mall Collection (APAP-067) and the records of Save the Pine Bush (APAP-125). A complete list of related collections is available at the subject guide for Conservation and the Environment.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is organized into the following series:
Series 1: Subject Files, 1969, 1971, 1974-1983, 1985-1986.
Series 2: Legal Papers, 1964, 1972, 1974, 1977-1983.
Series 3: DEC Exhibits, 1973, 1979-1980.
Series 4: News Clippings, 1975, 1977-1985, 1987.
Series 1 and 2 are arranged alphabetically; series 3 is arranged by exhibit number; series 4 is arranged chronologically.
Subject and Genre Headings
Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Architecture; Albany, New York; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Social Activists and Public Advocates; Neighborhood and Community Associations; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Conservation and the Environment; Architecture; Albany, New York; Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates; Crossgates Mall; Shopping malls; Urban development; Albany (N.Y.); Civil actions; Case files; Newspaper clippings
Container List
- Subject Files, 1969; 1971; 1974-1983; 1985-1986; 1; 1.5
  Arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains correspondence generated or received by Concerned Citizens Against Crossgates, petitions, fliers and ads relating to CCAC meetings, lists of CCAC speaking engagements and witnesses for CCAC. Also included are folders on the canidates for the 1980 Town of Guilderland elections. This series also contains data gathered on traffic at other malls and literature relating to residential property values.
  - CCAC Correspondence, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - CCAC Correspondence, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - CCAC Correspondence, Legal, 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - CCAC Correspondence concerning water permit, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - CCAC Correspondence from the town people, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - CCAC "Stop X Gate" Button., Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Crossgates: Cartoon, ca. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Crossgates: Effect on existing malls, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Crossgates: Grand opening of Jordan Marsh and Filene's, 1985 July 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Crossgates: Magazines, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Environmental Information, 1974; 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Environmental Conservation Commissioner, Peter Berle, Resignation, 1978; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fliers, ads, etc. of CCAC, 1979-1982 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fliers, ads, etc. of CCAC, 1979-1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Gary Nelson, Planning and Management consultant, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Guilderland Democratic Party, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Industrial Development Agency papers, 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Laws and regulations, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Letters from the public to CCAC regarding Crossgates, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Malls: Construction photographs, ca. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Malls: General discussions, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Malls: Public policy, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - McKownville becoming a village, Ideas, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Noise pollution and Danny Driscoll, 1978; 1980 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Petitions from people opposed to Crossgates, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pro-mall letters to CCAC, 1979-1981 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Property valuation studies and correspondence, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Public hearing information of CCAC, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Pyramid Company, Background information, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Real Property Tax, Exemptions, 1976; 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Residential property values, literature, 1977-1980 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Speeches and appearances of CCAC, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Stores interested in Crossgates, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Suburban Growth Theory, 1980; 1983; 1986 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Traffic data on other malls, 1977; 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Traffic references, 1971; 1978-1980 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Town of Guilderland Election materials, 1979; 1980; 1981 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Anne Gafney, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Gordon Cannon, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: John Shea, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Town of Guilderland Election: Lindsy Childs, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Town of Guilderland Master Plan, 1969; 1975; 1980-1982 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Town of Guilderland related papers, 1979-1981 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Town of Guilderland: Testimony of Margaret McKinley, 1978; 1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Town of Guilderland: Town Board meetings and correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Town of Guilderland: Traffic Data, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - V. Zappala & Co. v. Pyramid Co., 1981 and Interstate Properties v. Pyramid Co. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Witnesses for CCAC., 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Legal Papers, 1964; 1972; 1974; 1977-1983; 2; 1.75
  This series includes copies of Department of Environmental Conservation (DEC) commissioned studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment, society, and wildlife. This series also contains draft environmental impact statements, documentation for water merger appeals, and copies of Zoning Board records. Included in this series are 14 folders of maps that show plans for improvements on the mall site and surrounding area. There are nine folders containing documentation of CCAC suits against Robert F. Flacke.
  - DEC Air Quality Analysis (DOT), 1982 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - DEC Applicant's response to 11/28/80 DEC decision, 1981 February 9 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - DEC Briefs, Applications of Pyramid Crossgates Company, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - DEC Briefs, decisions, post-decision and correspondence, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - DEC Correspondence and final decision, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation, actual permits, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation cases pertaining to other malls, 1979; 1980; 1982 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation, final submissions, 1981-1982 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, reform of part 621, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, reform of part 624, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation Law, briefs and correspondence, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - DEC Environmental Conservation notices, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - DEC Hearing submissions related to testimony before DEC, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - DEC Interrogatories, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - DEC Reply briefs in regard to application of Pyramid Co., DEC case 401-09-S002, 1980 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - DEC Subpoenas of DEC officials during hearings, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - DEC Summary of Facts submitted by Pyramid Co. to Judge Dickerson in connection with applications for permits from DEC, 1980 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Maps: Layout Plan, 1979 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Maps: Profiles (of detention ponds), 1979 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Maps: Drainage Area Map-before development, 1979 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Maps: Plan and Profile, 1979 June 12 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20-Highway Improvement Plan, 1979 October 16 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Maps: Washington Ave. Extension and Fuller road I-90 ramps, Highway Improvement Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Maps: Utilities Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Maps: Air Quality Data Plan, 1979 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Maps: Drainage Area Map--after development, 1979 October 17 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Maps: Highway Maintenance and Jurisdiction Plan, Alternative 4, 1979 November 08 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20--Highway Improvement Plan, 1981 July 07 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Maps: U.S. Route 20--Highway Improvement Plan, 1981 July 17 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Maps: Highway Maintenance and Jurisdiction Plan, 1979 November 08 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Maps: Town of Guilderland, 1981 March 05 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Environment: Draft Environmental Impact statement, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Environment: Environmental Assessment Form (EAF), Pyramid Co. application, Part 1, 1979 May 30 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Environment: Draft Environmental statement, incomplete, 1979-1980 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--air (Part l), 1978-1980; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--air (Part ll), 1978-1980; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment-air (Part lll), 1978-1980; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--society, 1979; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the environment--wildlife, 1979; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Studies on the impact of Crossgates on the traffic, 1980; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Studies on the impact of the economy, 1977; Study completed for the Crossgates Group (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Water Merger information, 1964; 1974; 1978; 1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Water Merger vote, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing water merger vote, 1972; 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Water Merger: CCAC suit appealing water merger vote, 1979; 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Water Merger: Suit appealing water merger vote, 1982-1983 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, CCAC correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals, minutes of proceeding, 1981 September 09 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Zoning Board: Pyramid's applications before the Zoning Board, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Zoning Board: Susan Foster, concerning special permit for zoning, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Zoning Board: Albany Co. Planning Board, zoning and subdivision reviews and correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Zoning Board: CCAC v. Guilderland about rezoning, 1980; 1981-1982 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Zoning Board: CCAC suit against Town of Guilderland Zoning Board, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Zoning Board of Appeals suit, Pyramid v. ZBA, October and November, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Zoning Board papers, suit, 1980-1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke and William J. Dickerson, Supreme Court, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, DEC, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court, 1980-1981 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - CCAC suit against Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court, 1981 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Supreme Court decision, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Appelate, 1980-1982 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, Court of Appeals, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, volume 1, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - CCAC v. Robert F. Flacke, volume 2, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- DEC Exhibits, 1973; 1979-1980; 3; 1.0
  Arranged by exhibit number.
  This series contains exhibits presented at DEC hearings from 1979-80. Included in this series are letters, surveys, reports, photographs, maps, and resumes of expert witnesses. The first folder contains a list of all exhibits.
  - List of exhibits, 1-333b, 1979 August 13-1980 July 24; This document is available online (http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/findaids/apap057/Series3Box4_List.pdf) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Exhibits #1-29, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Exhibits #30-52, 1978; 1980 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Exhibits #55-79, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Exhibits #80-99., Undated; Exhibits 94-98 not found, 03/17/06, acs. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Exhibits #100-119, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Exhibits #120-139, 1978; 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Exhibits #140-159, 1973; 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Exhibits #160-179, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Exhibits #180-199, 1978; 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Exhibits #200-219, Undated; Exhibits 207-208B are available online (http://library.albany.edu/speccoll/findaids/apap057/Series3Box4_Exhibits207_208b.pdf) (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Exhibits #220-239, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Exhibits #240-259, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Exhibits #260-279, 1960-1977; 1980 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Exhibits #280-299, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Exhibits #300-333b., 1973; 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Service list; and possible list of CCAC members., 1980 July 14 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- News Clippings, 1975; 1977-1985; 1987; 4; 0.8
  Arranged chronologically.
  This series contains copies and originals of News Clippings primarily from the Albany Times Union and Schenectady Gazette.
  - News Clippings, 1975 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - News Clippings, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - News Clippings, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 4-5)
  - News Clippings, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6-10)
  - News Clippings, 1981 (Box 6, Folder 1-2)
  - News Clippings, 1982 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - News Clippings, 1983 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - News Clippings, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - News Clippings, 1987 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Pine Bush, News Clippings, 1977-1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)